<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
            <channel>
            <title>观察者网</title>
            <link>http://www.guancha.cn/mainnews-sp/</link>
            <description></description>
<item>
<guid>e5e2f9fa4543e656589dc5877be09147</guid>
<title>当前经济工作的几个重大问题</title>
<link>https://www.guancha.cn/XiJinPing/2023_02_17_680194.shtml</link>
<content:encoded>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;content all-txt&quot;&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
当前经济工作的几个重大问题※
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
习近平
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.guancha.cn/news/mainland/2023/02/17/20230217092220653.jpg&quot; title=&quot;点击查看大图&quot; class=&quot;bigimg&quot; width=&quot;530&quot;&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:#999999;&quot;&gt;2022年12月15日至16日，中央经济工作会议在北京举行。中共中央总书记、国家主席、中央军委主席习近平出席会议并发表重要讲话。新华社记者 鞠鹏/摄&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
明年经济工作千头万绪，需要从战略全局出发，抓主要矛盾，从改善社会心理预期、提振发展信心入手，抓住重大关键环节，纲举目张做好工作。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;（一）着力扩大国内需求&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
总需求不足是当前经济运行面临的突出矛盾。必须大力实施扩大内需战略，采取更加有力的措施，使社会再生产实现良性循环。我国通过扩大内需有效应对了1998年亚洲金融危机、2008年国际金融危机、2020年以来新冠肺炎疫情冲击，积累了成功经验，要优化政策举措，充分发挥消费的基础作用和投资的关键作用。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
一是把恢复和扩大消费摆在优先位置。我国新型工业化、信息化、城镇化、农业现代化深入推进，消费日益成为拉动经济增长的基础性力量。要增强消费能力，改善消费条件，创新消费场景，使消费潜力充分释放出来。消费是收入的函数，要多渠道增加城乡居民收入，特别是要提高消费倾向高、但受疫情影响大的中低收入居民的消费能力。要合理增加消费信贷，支持住房改善、新能源汽车、养老服务、教育医疗文化体育服务等消费。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
二是通过政府投资和政策激励有效带动全社会投资。当前，民间投资预期较弱，政府投资必须发挥好引导作用，这是应对经济周期性波动的有力工具。政府投资要在打基础、利长远、补短板、调结构上加大力度，加快实施“十四五”重大工程，加强交通、能源、水利、农业、信息等基础设施建设，加强区域间基础设施联通。要支持城市群和都市圈建设现代化基础设施体系，实施城市更新行动、乡村建设行动。要加大科技和产业投资，超前开展重大科技基础设施和关键核心技术研发能力建设。政策性金融要发挥逆周期调节作用，加大对符合国家发展规划和产业政策导向重大项目的融资支持力度，兼顾好经济效益和社会效益。要放宽民间投资市场准入，鼓励和吸引更多民间资本参与国家重大工程和补短板项目建设。要加强项目储备和前期工作，强化要素保障。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
要继续发挥出口对经济的支撑作用。要稳住对发达国家出口，扩大对新兴经济体出口，提升加工贸易水平，提高出口附加值，扩大服务贸易，发展数字贸易，巩固拓展新能源汽车等新产业出口优势，积极扩大先进技术、重要设备、能源资源等产品进口，发挥好中欧班列作用，加快建设贸易强国。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;（二）加快建设现代化产业体系&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
我们要练好内功、站稳脚跟。我国有世界最完整的产业体系和潜力最大的内需市场，要切实提升产业链供应链韧性和安全水平，抓紧补短板、锻长板。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.guancha.cn/news/mainland/2023/02/17/20230217092238449.jpg&quot; title=&quot;点击查看大图&quot; class=&quot;bigimg&quot; width=&quot;530&quot;&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:#999999;&quot;&gt;2023年1月18日，中共中央总书记、国家主席、中央军委主席习近平在北京通过视频连线看望慰问基层干部群众，向全国各族人民致以新春的美好祝福。这是习近平通过视频连线，同北京新发地农产品批发市场的商户和采购年货的群众亲切交流。 新华社记者 李涛/摄&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
一是确保国民经济循环畅通。我国经济必须确保国家安全，确保基本民生，确保基础设施、基础产业总体正常运转。要大力提升粮食、能源资源安全保障能力，特别是要把粮食饭碗牢牢端在自己手上。要实施新一轮千亿斤粮食产能提升行动，向耕地和科技要产能，向国土资源要食物。要加强重要能源、矿产资源国内勘探开发和增储上产，统筹布局电力源网荷储，加快规划建设新型能源体系，支持企业“组团出海”，加快进口多元化。要提升国家战略物资储备保障能力。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
二是加快实现产业体系升级发展。要在重点领域提前布局，全面提升产业体系现代化水平，既巩固传统优势产业领先地位，又创造新的竞争优势。抓住全球产业结构和布局调整过程中孕育的新机遇，勇于开辟新领域、制胜新赛道。传统制造业是现代化产业体系的基底，要加快数字化转型，推广先进适用技术，着力提升高端化、智能化、绿色化水平。战略性新兴产业是引领未来发展的新支柱、新赛道。要加快新能源、人工智能、生物制造、绿色低碳、量子计算等前沿技术研发和应用推广，支持专精特新企业发展。要大力发展数字经济，提升常态化监管水平，支持平台企业在引领发展、创造就业、国际竞争中大显身手。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;（三）切实落实“两个毫不动摇”&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
一段时间以来，社会上对我们是否还搞社会主义市场经济、是否坚持“两个毫不动摇”有一些不正确甚至错误的议论。我们必须亮明态度、决不含糊，始终坚持社会主义市场经济改革方向，坚持“两个毫不动摇”。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
一是深化国资国企改革，提高国企核心竞争力。国企改革三年行动已见成效，要根据形势变化，以提高核心竞争力和增强核心功能为重点，谋划新一轮深化国有企业改革行动方案。我国经营性国有资产规模大，一些企业资产收益率不高、创新能力不足，同国有资本和国有企业做强做优做大、发挥国有经济战略支撑作用的要求不相适应。要坚持分类改革方向，处理好国企经济责任和社会责任关系，健全以管资本为主的国资管理体制，发挥国有资本投资运营公司作用，以市场化方式推进国企整合重组，打造一批创新型国有企业。要完善中国特色国有企业现代公司治理，真正按市场化机制运营，加快建设世界一流企业。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
二是优化民营企业发展环境，促进民营经济发展壮大。民营经济对经济社会发展、就业、财政税收、科技创新等具有重要作用。要从制度和法律上把对国企民企平等对待的要求落下来，从政策和舆论上鼓励支持民营经济和民营企业发展壮大。要依法保护民营企业产权和企业家权益。要全面梳理修订涉企法律法规政策，持续破除影响平等准入的壁垒。要完善公平竞争制度，反对地方保护和行政垄断，为民营企业开辟更多空间。要加强中小微企业管理服务，支持中小微企业和个体工商户发展。各级领导干部要为民营企业解难题、办实事，构建亲清政商关系。国企、民企、外企都要依法合规经营。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;（四）更大力度吸引和利用外资&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
今年我国利用外资继续保持较快增长。纵观全球，发达国家和新兴经济体都把吸引和利用外资作为重大国策，招商引资国际竞争更加激烈。我们要推进高水平对外开放，依托我国超大规模市场优势，以国内大循环吸引全球资源要素，既要把优质存量外资留下来，还要把更多高质量外资吸引过来，提升贸易投资合作质量和水平。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
一是扩大市场准入。要合理缩减外资准入负面清单，加大现代服务业领域开放力度，发挥好自由贸易试验区、海南自由贸易港、各类开发区和保税区等开放平台的先行先试作用，已宣布的外资准入政策要抓紧落地见效。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
二是全面优化营商环境。要落实好外资企业国民待遇，促进公平竞争，保障外资企业依法平等参与政府采购、招投标、标准制定，加大知识产权和外商投资合法权益的保护力度。要积极推动加入《全面与进步跨太平洋伙伴关系协定》（CPTPP）和《数字经济伙伴关系协定》（DEPA）等高标准经贸协议，并主动对照相关规则、规制、管理、标准，深化国内相关领域改革。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
三是有针对性做好外资企业服务工作。要加强同外商沟通交流，为外商来华从事贸易投资洽谈提供最大程度的便利，同时也要推动经贸人员常态化走出去招商引资。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;（五）有效防范化解重大经济金融风险&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
我们必须坚持标本兼治、远近结合，牢牢守住不发生系统性风险底线。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
一是防范房地产业引发系统性风险。房地产对经济增长、就业、财税收入、居民财富、金融稳定都具有重大影响。要正确处理防范系统性风险和道德风险的关系，做好风险应对各项工作，确保房地产市场平稳发展。各地区和有关部门要扛起责任。要因城施策，着力改善预期，扩大有效需求，支持刚性和改善性住房需求，支持落实生育政策和人才政策，解决好新市民、青年人等住房问题，鼓励地方政府和金融机构加大保障性租赁住房供给，探索长租房市场建设。要坚持房子是用来住的、不是用来炒的定位，深入研判房地产市场供求关系和城镇化格局等重大趋势性、结构性变化，抓紧研究中长期治本之策，消除多年来“高负债、高杠杆、高周转”发展模式弊端，推动房地产业向新发展模式平稳过渡。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
二是防范化解金融风险。金融事关发展全局。要统筹好防范重大金融风险和道德风险，压实各方责任，及时加以处置，防止形成区域性、系统性金融风险。要加强党中央对金融工作集中统一领导，深化金融体制改革。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.guancha.cn/news/mainland/2023/02/17/20230217092303654.jpg&quot; title=&quot;点击查看大图&quot; class=&quot;bigimg&quot; width=&quot;530&quot;&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:#999999;&quot;&gt;2023年1月18日，中共中央总书记、国家主席、中央军委主席习近平在北京通过视频连线看望慰问基层干部群众，向全国各族人民致以新春的美好祝福。这是习近平通过视频连线，同塔里木油田公司轮南油气储运中心西气东输第一站克拉集气区员工亲切交流。 新华社记者 李涛/摄&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
三是防范化解地方政府债务风险。要压实省级政府防范化解隐性债务主体责任，加大存量隐性债务处置力度，优化债务期限结构，降低利息负担，稳步推进地方政府隐性债务和法定债务合并监管，坚决遏制增量、化解存量。要禁止各种变相举债行为，防范地方国有企事业单位“平台化”。要加强对融资平台公司的综合治理，推动分类转型。要深化财税体制改革，完善财政转移支付体系，健全省以下财政体制，稳步推进地方税体系建设，夯实地方基本财力和自我发展能力。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
明年还有许多重要工作要做。要全面推进乡村振兴，稳定粮食生产，坚决防止出现规模性返贫，畅通城乡要素流动和循环，建设宜居宜业和美乡村。要围绕构建高水平社会主义市场经济体制、推进高水平对外开放，谋划新一轮全面深化改革。要筹备办好第三届“一带一路”国际合作高峰论坛，推动共建“一带一路”高质量发展。要深入实施区域重大战略和区域协调发展战略，促进优势互补、各展其长。要推动经济社会发展绿色转型，协同推进降碳、减污、扩绿、增长，创造条件加快能耗“双控”转向碳排放“双控”制度，持续深入打好蓝天、碧水、净土保卫战，建设美丽中国。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
※这是习近平总书记2022年12月15日在中央经济工作会议上讲话的一部分。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<guid>b012c02bb90a1d679af46f8ddcdc9fe7</guid>
<title>关心粮食安全没错，但不该被河南小麦抢收这样的舆论带了节奏</title>
<link>https://www.guancha.cn/norlanseed/2023_06_05_695454.shtml</link>
<content:encoded>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;content all-txt&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
【文/观察者网专栏作者 合川老农民】
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
俗话说，小麦一生有五怕：
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;content-quote&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
正月怕暖，二月怕寒，三月怕霜，四月怕风，五月怕雨。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
而今年的五月雨，就最容易形成所谓的“烂场雨”。烂场雨的特点是雨势非常大，持续时间较长，往往导致种植场地积水严重，麦田里的麦子大面积倒伏、发霉发芽，最后烂在场子里。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
最近河南地区遭遇了10年来最严重的烂场雨，对当地的夏粮农收造成了不小的影响。同时，一些别有用心的自媒体趁机在网上造势，比如“100辆收割机被拦在高速公路上，人祸大于天灾”，又比如“老农民看着地里发霉的麦子痛声大哭，这国怎……”。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
类似套路我们已见惯不怪，但真要从根本上对其形成辨别能力，就应该稍微系统地了解一下我国关于夏收的一些制度性保障与配套。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
农业是看天吃饭的行道，至少以当前人类的技术水平来看，看天的成分依然占有很大比例。烂场雨也不是今年才突然冒出来的，早已是农耕的常客。到了今天会被如此重视，可能主要还是因为粮食安全在当下有着特殊意义，社会有着广泛关注度。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
既然烂场雨并非新鲜事，政府已经有了一套行之有效的应对方法。于此，笔者粗略地跟大家谈谈我国政府是从哪些方面来保障夏粮农收的。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;1. 农机保障体系&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
过去农村因为人多，单户种植规模不大，遇到烂场雨这种恶劣天气，家里老少几代人一起去田里抢收粮食，或者生产队里互帮互助，通过“人海战术”便能度过危机。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
但现今的农村人口凋敝，农田规模又相对扩大，靠空巢老人和留守儿童显然无法支撑抢收的需求。在这种情况下，农用机械就成为承担农收劳动的主力；为了保护这些工业时代的新型劳动力的正常投入，农机保障体系就变得非常重要。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.guancha.cn/news/mainland/2023/06/04/20230604164246118.png&quot; title=&quot;点击查看大图&quot; class=&quot;bigimg&quot; width=&quot;530&quot;&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:#666666;&quot;&gt;常见的轮式收割农机&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
农机保障体系粗略地分为三个方面：
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
1) 农机设备的生产供给、新技术的研发与投入。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
农机设备是支撑农业现代化的一个关键因素，因此全国各农业大省各自都有相应的农机设备相关配置规划。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
以四川省为例，截止今年，全省农机总动力达4753.58万千瓦，大中型拖拉机、谷物联合收割机保有量分别达到7.45万台、3.74万台。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.guancha.cn/news/mainland/2023/06/04/20230604164349811.png&quot; title=&quot;点击查看大图&quot; class=&quot;bigimg&quot; width=&quot;530&quot;&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:#666666;&quot;&gt;四川省“十四五”现代农业装备推进方案&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
根据《四川省“十四五”现代农业装备推进方案（2021-2025年》，省政府将以成都、德阳、绵阳、乐山为重点，推动农机装备产业园建设，并在成渝农业带布局建设农机装备制造研发基地，打造高产值的智能农机装备龙头企业，以保障川内的农业机械设备的供应和维护，这就是将农机的造血能力本地化。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.guancha.cn/news/mainland/2023/06/04/20230604164441489.png&quot; title=&quot;点击查看大图&quot; class=&quot;bigimg&quot; width=&quot;530&quot;&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:#666666;&quot;&gt;四川省十四五农业机械化截止2025年主要目标&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
2) 农业设备的维护，操作培训。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
光有生产还不够，服务要与生产配套，特别是提高农机社会化服务能力，把农机相关服务沉下去。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
在此必须强调一点，相较于传统农业，现代农业对于“服务”的需求是极高的。主要原因是，现代农业在生产规模上集约化，需要机械、信息化管理技术的导入，客观上对种植者的综合素质提出了更高的要求。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
同样以四川省为例，上述文件中还提到“1+1”农机社会化服务模式，即1个现代粮油园区至少建成一个“全程机械化+综合农事”服务中心。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
再进一步，又有了“一乡一社”的要求，即把农机合作社的服务单元扎根到乡级单位。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.guancha.cn/news/mainland/2023/06/04/20230604170056139.png&quot; title=&quot;点击查看大图&quot; class=&quot;bigimg&quot; width=&quot;530&quot;&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:#666666;&quot;&gt;雅安市名山区绿新农机服务专业合作社&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
3）农机应急保障组织体系的建立。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
在保障农机设备的造血能力、农机服务能力之外，对于设备的合理调配以及人力的足额投入也是极为重要的。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
无论是此前得克萨斯州的雪灾，还是俄亥俄州的危险化学品泄漏，都让我们明白一个道理，那就是在大型灾害面前，靠所谓的自由市场去调节往往是杯水车薪。这时候，就一定需要强有力的行政力量作为保障。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
农机应急保障体系，就是以行政力量托底，来保障遭遇灾害时对于农机设备的调配需求以及人力投入需求。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
以江西省为例，今年该省于省市县三级农业农村部门成立农机应急保障办公室，在单季水稻种植面积5000亩以上的乡镇成立服务队。在面临紧急情况时服务队将接受农业农村部门统一指挥调度，通过政府购买服务等方式进行支持。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.guancha.cn/news/mainland/2023/06/04/20230604170115335.png&quot; title=&quot;点击查看大图&quot; class=&quot;bigimg&quot; width=&quot;530&quot;&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:#666666;&quot;&gt;江西省推动建立农机应急保障体系&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;2. 高标准农田建设推广&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
场地积水，是导致小麦发霉、发芽的主因，同时也会影响收割机下地抢收。因此，完善农田的除涝排水相关配套设施，有利于应对“烂场雨”这种连续阴雨天气。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
高标准农田是国家自2019年以来重点推进的农业基础设施建设项目，其目的是为农业进一步导入现代化的管理技术打下基础，而相较于普通农田更优异的排涝性能就是其中的重要指标之一。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
以四川省地方标准为例，高标准农田排涝设计标准不低于10a（10年）一遇洪水重现期。设计暴雨历时（雨下多久）和排出时间（积水排多久）应达到：旱作区1～3天的暴雨1～3天排除。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.guancha.cn/news/mainland/2023/06/04/20230604170158965.png&quot; title=&quot;点击查看大图&quot; class=&quot;bigimg&quot;&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:#666666;&quot;&gt;一种高标准农田的水利设计&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.guancha.cn/news/mainland/2023/06/04/20230604170215815.png&quot; title=&quot;点击查看大图&quot; class=&quot;bigimg&quot; width=&quot;530&quot;&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:#666666;&quot;&gt;一种高标准农田的排水沟设计图&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
若更广泛地普及高标准农田的建设，类似河南今年的烂场雨所造成的积水问题会得到极大缓解，有效提高抢收作物的效率。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
截止2023年4月，我国已累计完成高标准农田超过10亿亩。随着高标准农田的逐步普及，相信今后应对烂场雨这种积水问题会得到整体的改善。
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<guid>92f56b6934bdea821675e072559028b0</guid>
<title>帝国主义的悲哀：暴力被打败了，金钱快要不灵了，只剩谎言了</title>
<link>https://www.guancha.cn/ZiZheng/2023_06_05_695453.shtml</link>
<content:encoded>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;content all-txt&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
【文/观察者网专栏作者 子政】
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
为期两天的IISS新加坡第20届香格里拉对话会闭幕。不出所料，中国版《全球安全倡议》与美国一直以来关于安全与稳定的谎言套话迎头相撞。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
中国国防部长李尚福在4日的主旨发言中郑重提出，中方倡导共同、综合、合作、可持续的安全观，愿与各方强化亚太命运共同体意识，推动区域安全合作健康发展，努力建设开放、包容、透明、平等的地区安全合作架构。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.guancha.cn/news/mainland/2023/06/05/20230605075047811.png&quot; title=&quot;点击查看大图&quot; class=&quot;bigimg&quot; width=&quot;530&quot;&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:#666666;&quot;&gt;李尚福在第20届香格里拉对话会上作大会发言（图/新华网）&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
这当然不是美方所乐见的，它所坚持的当然还是霸权主义和强权政治，还是把自己的意志强加于人，把自己的利益凌驾于人，把自己的安全建立在别人的不安全之上。而政客们那些貌似公正的套话不过是掩盖这个实质的谎言。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
在当前这个时机，在亚太地区紧张局势不断升温、国际舆论关于第三次世界大战的讨论越来越热的大背景下，中美双方关于安全问题的话语都已经不是说说而已了，背后实际上都连接着各自的底线，可调和的空间日益逼仄。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
但问题是，中国正面推出《全球安全倡议》，关乎全球最高优先级事务，并且开宗明义，表明了对各国人民福祉、世界和平发展、人类前途命运的真诚关切，对当前全球“和平赤字、发展赤字、安全赤字、治理赤字加重”问题的真切忧虑。其中的各项具体主张，都完全出以公心，并无夹杂中国自身利益的私货，也因此而得到了国际社会的普遍认可。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
所以按道理讲，只要真正站在全球的立场上，抱着全人类命运与共的情怀，一定不会拒绝这个倡议。在这种情况下，对《倡议》内容的接受与不接受，实际上具有了检验立场的潜在含义。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
《倡议》中明确表示将“秉持开放包容原则，欢迎和期待各方参与，共同丰富倡议内涵，积极探索开展新形式新领域合作。”而从美方的表态来看，这个国家不仅不会响应，不仅要继续抛出各种谎言扰乱视听，还必定会采取具体行动阻止这个局面的发生。那么，其基本立场也就昭然若揭了。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
为什么会在涉及全球安全这个具有最高优先级并直接关系到战争与和平、生存与毁灭的重大事务上仍然出现基本立场上的对立？难道这个世界上确实存在某种置各国人民福祉、世界和平发展、人类前途命运于不顾，宁肯让全球陷入持续动荡乃至全面战争也在所不辞的特殊立场？也确实存在如果自身愿望不能实现，宁肯让全世界一起毁灭的特殊利益集团？
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;帝国主义仍是帝国主义&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
很遗憾，以上这两个问题本不应该成为问题。而之所以竟然成为问题，很多人不愿意相信，只是因为今天这个时代早已是一个由谎言和人为编织的幻象所主导的时代，重大的事实真相被各种似是而非的说法层层叠叠地笼罩着，难以探寻。若倒退回一百多年前帝国主义横行无忌的时代，这两个问题其实原本就不需要问。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
帝国主义的基本政治哲学本来就是只要自己活而不要别人活，当帝国主义分子觊觎他人的家园土地时，他们最初的做法就是把那块土地上的人全部杀光，把土地和财物据为己有。当然，他们有个说法：那些被杀的人都是坏人，好的土地应该留给好人。而好与坏的标准来自他们自己，或者是宗教的，或者是种族的，或者是政治的。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
这个时期的一个标志性人物是19世纪70-80年代曾担任过美国陆军总司令的菲利普·谢里登，他因指挥了一系列屠杀印第安人的战争而出名，而真正让他被记入史册的是他那句“名言”：“唯一好的印第安人是死去的印第安人。”
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.guancha.cn/news/internet/2023/06/05/20230605075156522.jpg&quot; title=&quot;点击查看大图&quot; alt=&quot;点击查看大图&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;374&quot;&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:#666666;&quot;&gt;菲利普·谢里登（资料图/维基百科）&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
这种老式的帝国主义原本会一直持续下去，因为全世界反帝统一战线还远未形成反制力量，而整个世界也原本就是帝国主义和反帝主义两种运动的你死我活。在这种局面下，不难想象，关于全球安全的概念以及共同、综合、合作、可持续的新型安全观，根本不会出现。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
但历史并没有沿着那条老路走下去，进入20世纪之后，帝国主义国家之间爆发了同样你死我活的战争。按照一种较新的历史观，这两次世界大战实际上是一场战争，加上中间的间歇期共计31年，最终以盎格鲁-撒克逊式帝国主义的胜利而告终。
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<guid>273d1d33659493aae25bce3979c42ce1</guid>
<title>血战的各种意义：为了阿尔乔莫夫斯克，真的值得吗？</title>
<link>https://www.guancha.cn/dayiwan/2023_06_05_695450.shtml</link>
<content:encoded>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;content all-txt&quot;&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
【文/观察者网专栏作者 大伊万】
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
2023年5月20日，俄军瓦格纳集群宣布，历经旷日持久的血战，阿尔乔莫夫斯克（巴赫穆特）的城市围廓已被瓦格纳完全夺取。据瓦格纳集群自身统计，在长达半年之久的阿尔乔莫夫斯克之战中，其共击毙、击伤乌克兰军人超过10万，击毁乌军各型号坦克、步战车、反伏击车数百台，击毁、缴获各型装备无算，而瓦格纳集群自身也付出了4万余人伤亡的巨大代价。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
当然，鉴于瓦格纳集群对战果和损失的统计往往都有所夸大，目前阿尔乔莫夫斯克之战较为公认的伤亡数据为瓦格纳统计的中位数：乌军伤亡约5到7万人，俄军伤亡约2到3万人。但无论如何，考虑到战役持续时间、双方投入的作战资源和最终的损失数量，以及阿尔乔莫夫斯克本身的战略意义，可以说，阿尔乔莫夫斯克之战是俄乌军事冲突爆发以来最残酷的血战。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:#666666;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.guancha.cn/news/external/2023/06/03/20230603212754914.jpg&quot; title=&quot;点击查看大图&quot; class=&quot;bigimg&quot; width=&quot;530&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:#666666;&quot;&gt;俄军宣布占领阿尔乔莫夫斯克（巴赫穆特）（路透社报道截图）&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
阿尔乔莫夫斯克之战中，瓦格纳集群在强大的炮兵和航空兵掩护下，以前赴后继的决死冲锋，一点一点地消耗乌军的有生力量，一段一段地蚕食乌军所掌握的土地。乌军分毫不让，前前后后投入了40个旅/团/营的番号进入阿尔乔莫夫斯克，为这些部队补充的动员兵数量根本无法计算，投入的装备资源同样无法计算。我们不禁要问，俄乌两军血战阿尔乔莫夫斯克，这一切真的值得吗？
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;阿尔乔莫夫斯克绞肉机？&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
从今年初开始，“阿尔乔莫夫斯克绞肉机”就频频见于瓦格纳集群的官方说法中，且确实在一定程度上反映了战略现实。阿尔乔莫夫斯克之战始于去年10月，当时，俄军面临的战场态势相当不利：北线俄军大批合同兵因议价权过高，选择回国休假或者解除服役合同，导致哈尔科夫到卢甘斯克一线的俄军大唱“空城计”，整条战线上几乎没有机动兵力，关键节点巴拉克列亚甚至靠卢甘斯克的民兵团防守，位于斯拉维扬斯克北方的战役节点红利曼甚至只能靠特别用途预备役分队和顿涅茨克几个民兵营防守，后续撤离时，俄军搜遍了整条战线，才拿出四个营的战斗队进行接应。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
后续北线俄军尽管在斯瓦托到克雷缅纳亚一线稳定住了战线，但依然面临着部队新败、士气不高、实力下降的问题，而当面乌军却拥有超过10个旅战斗群的机动兵力，部队质量尚可，数量更是远超俄军，加上赫尔松之战结束后乌军又得到了5个以上旅的机动部队，等于乌军得以自由选择一个新的战役进攻方向，这些兵力无论是投向斯瓦托、斯塔洛博斯克抑或梅利托波尔，以当时俄军的实力，都够喝一壶的，搞不好俄军去年的战果就被基本上清零了。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
因此，纵观战略全局，瓦格纳集群在此时开启阿尔乔莫夫斯克之战，客观上起到了打乱乌军战略布局的作用。乌军的作战风格一向以“寸土不丢”著称，加上阿尔乔莫夫斯克本身的战略地位也相当重要，因此，面对瓦格纳集群远接近地的猛攻，乌军只得抽调一部分宝贵的机动兵力投向阿尔乔莫夫斯克，用于稳定战线。乌军机动兵力总计也不过15到20个旅，每抽调走一个旅，就等于给其它战线上的俄军减轻了一个旅的压力。比如，当时作为北线反攻主力使用的乌军重要部队机92旅、机93旅、坦克17旅、预备坦克4旅，以及作为赫尔松反攻主力使用的山地128旅等，均被抽调到了阿尔乔莫夫斯克。这些兵力的投入确实一度稳定住了当地战线，使瓦格纳集群在去年十月至今年一月的三个月中推进缓慢；但另一方面，这些机动部队的离开，极大地影响了乌军其它战线的战役进攻，从去年十一月起，乌军在各条战线上的进攻基本停止，预定实施的扎波罗热反攻也没有进行。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
更令人惊奇的是，乌克兰军队起初只是抽调少部分机动兵力驰援阿尔乔莫夫斯克，后来却似乎越来越入戏、越来越上头，将阿尔乔莫夫斯战役变成了全军大轮战，几乎乌军所有有战斗力的部队都到此轮战了一个遍。三月，俄军对阿尔乔莫夫斯克呈包围态势，泽连斯基严令乌军陆军司令希尔斯基死守。此后，乌军更如输红了眼的赌徒，将大量原本可用于敌后破袭、侦察渗透、目标引导的特种作战部队投入了阿尔乔莫夫斯克，和俄军打起了巷战，这种把特种部队当做普通步兵使用的骚操作令人目瞪口呆。说不定连瓦格纳集群自己都没有想到，乌军竟然对阿尔乔莫夫斯克如此上头，以至于打到了所有兵力残缺不全、全军只剩下9个北约旅基本齐装满员、连预定的新一轮“大反攻”都畏难退缩的情况。阿尔乔莫夫斯克之战不仅在战役层面上发挥了重要作用，在战略层面上甚至一定程度地扭转了俄乌两军的战略全局和力量对比。一言以蔽之，去年十月到今年五月俄乌两军局势逆转，由瓦格纳集群打造的“阿尔乔莫夫斯克绞肉机”功不可没。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
而战术层面呢？我们都知道，乌克兰军队有两大战术优势：一是有无穷无尽的“天灵盖”，二是有东乌地区的城市堡垒。前者虽良莠不齐，但面对数量更少的俄军，起码能够做到以数量换质量，靠给俄军放血来阻滞其前进步伐；后者更被乌军视为阻滞俄军进攻的“法宝”，以至于东乌地区别说是个城市了，连个村儿乌军都能把它给筑垒化。乌军在阿尔乔莫夫斯克，打的也是同样的算盘：靠苏勒达尔、欧泊汀、克里希奇夫卡等村，辅以野战筑城，阻滞瓦格纳的野战进攻，在必要的情况下，将瓦格纳放进阿尔乔莫夫斯克打巷战，靠巷战来拉近、抹平俄乌两军的战斗力差距，再靠巷战来消耗原本在数量上就处于下风的俄军，尽量把俄军的“血”都给放干耗尽。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
但是，饶是乌军这算盘打的噼里啪啦响，想得一切都很完美，阿尔乔莫夫斯克之战最后的胜利者依然是俄军。这似乎表明，只要俄军决心攻克某座城市，最后终能成功。对乌军而言，这意味着其在乌东地区组织防御的两大“法宝”在有心攻坚的俄军面前失灵了；而对俄军而言，这证明了俄军的战术能力，使之建立起对付城市筑垒的信心。未来，俄军将要面对斯拉维扬斯克-克拉玛托尔斯克-德鲁士科夫卡组成的城市筑垒，阿尔乔莫夫斯克之战的胜利对俄军的意义非同小可。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;阿尔乔莫夫斯克，真的不重要吗？&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
从今年年初苏勒达尔丢失后，在北约集团、乌军的公关宣传中，阿尔乔莫夫斯克的重要性就一直在“战略要地”和“无关紧要的小村庄”之间摇摆，处于薛定谔状态。乌军能守住阿尔乔莫夫斯克时，此地就是“乌克兰东部的战略要地”，万万不可丢失；等到俄军在南北各战线上取得了进展，乃至最终攻取阿尔乔莫夫斯克后，此地就变成了“乌克兰东部的一座无关紧要的小村庄”，俄军把大量的兵力投入到这里流血，只是为了做给俄罗斯国内看，连基辅政府高官们都在大言不惭地表示，乌军在阿尔乔莫夫斯克“摧毁了俄军几乎所有可用的储备”，俄军花了八个月时间才打下一座数万人的小镇，说难听点，“够干啥的”。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
阿尔乔莫夫斯克真的不重要吗？说该城不重要那当然是假的。毕竟从乌军顿巴斯联合战役集群向东部两州发起战役进攻的预定布势来看，阿尔乔莫夫斯克其实应是乌军重要的作战基地。此地有两条重要的战略公路：通向伊洛瓦伊斯克的M03高速公路，和通向利西昌斯克的T0302公路。以前者为主要进攻轴向，可经过伊洛瓦伊斯克和斯维特洛达尔西克防御弧线，从顿涅茨克和卢甘斯克最脆弱的结合部，将两州一劈为二、然后分别吃掉；以后者为进攻轴向，则可以直趋北顿涅茨克和利西昌斯克，控扼卢甘斯克这两座最为重要的工业重镇。
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:#666666;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.guancha.cn/news/external/2023/06/03/20230603212848529.jpg&quot; title=&quot;点击查看大图&quot; class=&quot;bigimg&quot; width=&quot;530&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:#666666;&quot;&gt;阿尔乔莫夫斯克及周边地图（图源：BBC）&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<guid>b6b84b386a9526f605001e4698880c75</guid>
<title>Guancha interview with Cristovam Buarque</title>
<link>https://www.guancha.cn/CristovamBuarque/2023_06_05_695449.shtml</link>
<content:encoded>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;content all-txt&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From April 12 to 15, Brazilian President Lula paid a state visit to China. During the visit, China and Brazil signed a joint statement on deepening their comprehensive strategic partnership.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Lula believes that China is crucial to his goal of revitalizing Brazilian industry, and he plans to promote a number of policies, including: encouraging Chinese companies to establish new factories in Brazil, attracting more Chinese investment, and reducing the extent of dollarization in foreign trade, among others.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over the past decade or so, Brazil has has been hit by a number of economic crises. Its traditional economic model of exporting primary resources, such as agricultural products, has not proven capable of further lifting Brazil&#x27;s economic progress.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Cristovam Buarque, member of the South Centre&#x27;s board, former Brazilisn Minister of Education and Senator, recently sat down for an interview with Guancha. He believes that education is key to Brazil&#x27;s further development, also expressing his views on how China and Brazil can further expand bilateral and multilateral cooperation, and how the world can adopt to a new multipolar world order.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.guancha.cn/news/origin/2023/06/01/20230601163007185.jpg&quot; title=&quot;点击查看大图&quot; class=&quot;bigimg&quot; width=&quot;530&quot;&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:#666666;&quot;&gt;Guancha&#x27;s interview with Cristovam Buarque&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Below is a lightly edited transcript of the interview:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Guancha: In politics, you have consistently advocated for the importance of education in solving Brazil&#x27;s medium and long term problems. Could you briefly describe your proposal?&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Cristovam Buarque:&lt;/strong&gt; First of all, it&#x27;s a pleasure to be here, and wonderful to receive this question. Many times, they don&#x27;t put this question to me. But I think it&#x27;s very important to talk about that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For many years, decades, we have been saying to the people, to the world, that the most important thing is the economy, is production. We have been forgetting that education is the main vector of progress. We need education, and not just professional education, but basic education, the education of the whole population. We need that, first of all to give efficiency to the economic process, and we need schools to have the same quality of education, in order to achieve a better social function. Education is basic to the economy and is basic to society. We need education to produce more and we need education to distribute production better. This is what I have been discussing in Brazil during my whole career as a politician.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Guancha: Could you describe the specific challenges facing Brazilian education system?&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Cristovam Buarque: &lt;/strong&gt;The specific challenge facing Brazilian educational system is to lead with two targets: to be among the betters in the PISA international evaluation, and to have educational social equality, such that poor children experience the same quality of schooling as rich children. To fulfill these two purposes, the challenge is to move from 6000 municipal systems to one national system.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Guancha: Do you think the same applies broadly to other countries as well? What are some key challenges that education can solve?&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Cristovam Buarque:&lt;/strong&gt; I think that what I&#x27;ve been saying to Brazil, it&#x27;s worthwhile to the whole world, to any country, but many other countries have done that already. We have examples of countries that were very backwards some years ago, that grew up thanks to education: Finland is an example, South Korea is another example. Some cities in China are doing that, not the whole country yet, but China is doing what I recommend to Brazil, to start revolution in education per city. It&#x27;s impossible to make the revolution spread through a country as big as China and Brazil. I think that we have examples that we should follow, and China is one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Guancha: How should Brazil learn from China’s educational system?&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Cristovam Buarque:&lt;/strong&gt; We can learn from China’s national framework to basic education, which is different from our municipal system. A Chinese child is educated as Chinese, while a Brazilian child is educated as a municipal and individualistic person. The respect for Chinese history and heritage are present in the education of Chinese children and forms the Chinese ethos, while the Brazilian system is very much oriented to the individual and the present. We should also learn from the involvement of parents and greatparents in the care and education of Chinese children. Brazil leaves the education under total responsibility of teachers and school.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Guancha: China and Brazil are important trading partners, with Brazil&#x27;s export of agricultural and raw materials complementing China&#x27;s exports of machinery and electrical equipment. During president Lula&#x27;s recent visit to China, the two countries also signed a number of agreements on cooperation in energy, carbon credits, 5G network, financing and de-dollarization. What do you think is the most fruitful area for future cooperation? And how significant would cooperation between the two be for Brazil&#x27;s efforts to diversify its economy beyond commodities?&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.guancha.cn/news/external/2023/06/01/20230601163102438.jpg&quot; title=&quot;点击查看大图&quot; class=&quot;bigimg&quot; width=&quot;530&quot;&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:#666666;&quot;&gt;Lula&#x27;s April State visit to China&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Cristovam Buarque:&lt;/strong&gt; Brazil and China are today very tied. At least from the Brazilian point of view, China is the main partner in trading, a lot more important than, for example, United States and Argentina, the other two great partners. But we have been just trading in goods. We need more. For example, we need cooperation between our universities. We have to have programs, put together our students and Chinese students, our teachers and China&#x27;s teachers, to bring Chinese to Brazil, to send Brazilians to China. For many years, we have been looking to United States and Europe to study with a lot of scholarship. Let&#x27;s have more scholarships between Brazil and China.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We need cooperation also between scientific institutions. We have a very important group, for example, in the health system, health technology. We need to work closely with the Chinese scientists. We need cooperation in arts and culture, which would be very good. We need to bring to Brazil more artists from China and to send to China our artists. We need to translate more books from Chinese authors and to translate into Mandarin the work of Brazilian authors.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We have a world ahead to cooperate. Let&#x27;s not stop and do trade only. On trade, we already have good cooperation. Now we need to improve that to other sectors.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And finally, I think that we have to learn from China, the way China does politics. I&#x27;m not talking politics in this sense of congress. I&#x27;m talking also in the sense of government: China knows how to do projects. Brazil knows how to make the project but have terrible difficulty in executing the project. China can teach us how to execute our project. We have a lot to learn with China. And I think the cooperation would be good also to China.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Guancha: At the same time, Brazil has long standing security agreements with the US. In your opinion, how should Brazil balance relations with China and the US, which are both important partners to Brazil?&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Cristovam Buarque:&lt;/strong&gt; That would be an exercise in the future. We have to learn how to cooperate in this world, because we had the experience of mainly bilateral relationships, and a world with one pole, with one superpower.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today, happily, the United States is no more the center of international geopolitics, we have China, we have Europe. We have to learn how to develop other kinds of relations. But I have been saying something more than that. I think that even China has to learn.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Up to now, international diplomacy, politics and external policy were made regarding one country in the whole world. I think that now we have to learn to see the world before the country. I used to say that diplomacy was made to the time when the world was a group of countries. Today, I say that each country is a piece of the world. This require a different mindset for the diplomats, for politicians engaged in cooperation and relations with the other countries. Brazil and China can learn together and teach one another.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Guancha: China and Brazil are both key members of BRICS. How can both work to increase cooperation under this framework? Also, as two institutions both focused on promoting the interests of developing countries, how should the work of BRICS and the South Centre intersect and interact?&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Cristovam Buarque:&lt;/strong&gt; I proposed yesterday that the South Centre should invite the new president of BRICS bank, our Brazilian politician Dilma Rousseff, to come to South Centre to meet with us. We have to be inside the BRICS bank. I said that we have expertise, we have knowledge of the South. Let&#x27;s make that available to the BRICS bank. Regarding China and Brazil, we have something very good: we have a Brazilian president of BRICS bank, and the BRICS bank is in Shanghai, China.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.guancha.cn/news/external/2023/06/01/20230601163204364.jpg&quot; title=&quot;点击查看大图&quot; class=&quot;bigimg&quot; width=&quot;530&quot;&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:#666666;&quot;&gt; Dilma Rousseff takes office as the new President of the NDB in Shanghai, China on April 13, 2023. (PHOTO / AFP) &lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&#x27;s put together this cooperation, this coincidence, and let&#x27;s use the BRICS bank more. Personally, I think that we have to discuss a lot before that. I think that we should at least bring some other countries to BRICS and to BRICS bank. I think there are other countries that should be part of this experience, an experience that would change the world because it would be very important to this idea of a new geopolitics of multiple poles. BRICS is very important to this.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Guancha: What has been the effect of the war in Ukraine or Brazil, and how has China&#x27;s 12 point peace plan and proposed conflict mediation been received in Brazil?&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Cristovam Buarque:&lt;/strong&gt; This is something on which I have a different position as the Brazilian government today. I think that Brazil should not be involved in this conflict. There’s two ways to be involved. In the first way, Brazil is not: President Lula is quite clear, he’s not involved as a party militarily with one of the countries. This is OK.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But I have another position, no involvement even in the peace talks, because I think that Russia and Ukraine, they look so much like each other, in terms of literature, religion, language, history, that I think they will find that, in a certain moment, the internal forces in Russia and Ukraine will pressure their governments to come together and find the peace. Sure, if some countries, especially China and Europe, can help that, it would be okay.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But in the case of Lula, I have been saying that he has another role in the world. Lula should put a planetary statement to propose ways to come to three other peaces, different from the war between Russia and Ukraine: social peace, fighting against poverty; ecological peace, fighting for sustainable development; and migration peace, find a way to avoid millions of the people being forced to move from their country to another country, and some or most of the time not able find a new home. First of all, migrants might not arrive at the new country. Second, they might arrive but can not come in, because at the border they are stopped. And third, they will enter the new country, but will not be accepted legally.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Lula, I think, is the best man the world to produce a planetary statement. You might ask, but why not China? China is so special and so great and so big that perhaps it will not have this voice into the world: China is a hard power, Brazil can be a soft power, and we need soft power. For these 3 peaces, we need more soft power than hard power.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Guancha: Brazil&#x27;s economy has experienced a rather difficult decade in the 2010s, which has Led to rising domestic discontent and trouble. What do you think are the reasons behind this? How come Brazil overcome these challenges?&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Cristovam Buarque:&lt;/strong&gt; I think that the main reason why we’re in this situation with so rich a country is the lack of education, centuries without education for our people. The lack of education makes a country divided, socially divided. The main reason for the division of Brazil, we have to say Brazil is almost an Apartheid system, not racial apartheid as in South Africa since most of us are mixed; while there is some prejudice, some racism, but not racial apartheid.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But we do have a social apartheid, based on who has money, and who has no money. And having or not having money depends on having or not having education. And beside that, the lack of education is behind the fact that the politicians do not find a way to Brazil. We need education.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Beside that, we need better laws, to avoid corruption, and we need long term planning to our purpose. Brazil is very short term oriented. And this is a problem that we have to overcome.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Guancha: How would you overcome? &lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Cristovam Buarque:&lt;/strong&gt; We have two strategies. In the long term, improved education is key. And in the short term, let&#x27;s get together. Lula has been saying that to finish the Ukrainian war, we just have to put Putin and Zelensky on the same table. I think that in Brazil, he should do the same with the opposition, even the bad guys, sitting together to discuss, to talk and to find a middle way.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It will not to be Lula&#x27;s way, Lula&#x27;s party’s way, and I hope we will never have the Bolsonaro people in government again, but we have to talk. The answer to your question is talk, talk, talk, with modesty. No one knows exactly what to do. So, let&#x27;s discuss. Let&#x27;s having conversations, as Lula proposed between Putin and Zelensky.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.guancha.cn/news/external/2023/06/01/20230601163256427.jpg&quot; title=&quot;点击查看大图&quot; class=&quot;bigimg&quot; width=&quot;530&quot;&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:#666666;&quot;&gt;former Brazilian president Bolsonaro (PHOTO/Reuters)&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Guancha: This sounds kind of similar to what China has been proposing based on traditional Chinese philosophy, of trying to find common ground and trying to come together, include all views and not just holding some as superior to others.&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Cristovam Buarque:&lt;/strong&gt; Yes, China has a long history of this kind of conversation to find a way forwards. Perhaps we can go back to Confucius to find that. It is a tradition in China to talk, to discuss, to find the middle way. We need to learn from the Chinese.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Guancha: Going back to the three peaces you talked about, is the way to achieve that just through dialogue or does it also require acquire something else?&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Cristovam Buarque:&lt;/strong&gt; Other things, but especially speeches at the United Nations, conversation everywhere. Now, two of these three peaces, they come together. Social peace will bring migration peace. If you look to Syria, for example, the migration was because of the civil war, but usually in the world, migration is due to poverty, i.e. social reasons. This is the case of central America, for example. Then these two peaces, they come together: if we solve poverty, we solve migration.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For ecological peace, we need more than that. We need, in a certain way, a cultural revolution, a mind revolution, to abolish the way that gross national product is used as the indicator of civilization. No, civilization is a lot more than production. And one of the things we need a lot more of is the respect of nature, respect of ecology. It means we need sustainability. This peace is more difficult than the other two, and more urgent for humankind; social and migration peace is more urgent to poor people, to migrants, but ecology peace is more important than any other to humankind.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Guancha: While relations between China and Brazil have mostly been unaffected by Brazil&#x27;s internal politics, China and other countries have been concerned by post-election violence after the closely fought 2022 Brazil general election. Given the continued poor state of Brazil&#x27;s economy right now, should the international community be concerned about Brazil&#x27;s stability?&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Cristovam Buarque: &lt;/strong&gt;We have to be concerned a bit everywhere in the world, and especially in Brazil we have concerns, democracy is very fragile everywhere, in Brazil perhaps more than in a lot of other countries, but there&#x27;s no danger. Brazilian democracy is stable, at least for many years ahead.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Guancha: Recently there has been increased talk of decoupling and confrontation on the global stage. Key to this seems to be America&#x27;s desire to see all countries adopt a more western model of democracy, of governance, while China believes that development should be or is the most important democratic right of the people. So what do you think of these narratives?&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Cristovam Buarque: &lt;/strong&gt;Thank you very much for this question. I&#x27;d like to talk a lot more about that. America is a case of success from the point of view of a rich country, a powerful country, but it&#x27;s not from the point of view of sustainability, it&#x27;s not from the point of view of inclusion of the whole population to its benefits. They have a lot of exclusion, especially of a racial orientation: black people have it worse than white people, although there are a lot of poorer white people today. It&#x27;s a success from the point of view of the nation in the short term, in the past, but they have no reason to be an example to be followed forever by everyone. This is an arrogance, this is an error, a mistake to try to impose not only democracy but also the American way of life. The American way of life cannot be the way of life of humankind in the future, we need other ways to live instead.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.guancha.cn/news/external/2023/06/01/20230601163402691.png&quot; title=&quot;点击查看大图&quot; class=&quot;bigimg&quot; width=&quot;530&quot;&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:#666666;&quot;&gt;The Streets of San Francisco in the US (PHOTO/PGPF)&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the case of democracy, it was a very important factor to America, to some other countries, but each country has to look for their way of democracy. I put it like that, because democracy in its essence is the way to govern with the people. It&#x27;s not with the congress, with multiple parties, with elections, with electors as the king, not necessarily.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is why I was criticized a lot in Brazil, because I wrote a book where I put the idea of the Chinese mode of democracy. People didn&#x27;t like that in Brazil, many friends of mine were unhappy with this expression that I put there. But I use it, and I would say China has a mode of democracy, which is probably not the way Brazil would use. Brazil has to find a new way, but not necessarily the American or the French or the Japanese way, and they all have different modes of democracy anyways. America has to stop the idea that its democracy is the only way possible. We have other ways of democracy in the world, and China, I think, is trying to find its way.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
（Interview: Jersey Lee）
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;本文系观察者网独家稿件，文章内容纯属作者个人观点，不代表平台观点，未经授权，不得转载，否则将追究法律责任。关注观察者网微信guanchacn，每日阅读趣味文章。&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.guancha.cn/shiping-banner.jpg&quot; width=&quot;530px&quot;&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded>
</item>
</channel></rss>